Guide to the Medieval manuscript fragments, [ca. 800-ca. 1800]
Medieval manuscript fragments
- Historiated border from the Great Choir Book of Ferdinand and Isabella, Castile, Spain., Ca. 1479-1492.; Size: frame 510 x 260 mm (item 381 x 104 mm). (Mapcase-folder 8)
  Description: An elaborate historiated border on parchment, including the royal arms of Aragon and Castile surmounted by an eagle with a halo, together with the royal device of a bundle of seven arrows representing Ferdinand and a yoke representing Isabella (Y stood for yugo and for Ysabel and F stood for flechas and for Fernando, but there might also be some gender symbolism). Also present are all kinds of animals climbing through the foliage. This fragment comes from what was once a magnificent manuscript commissioned by Ferdinand of Aragon (1452-1516) and Isabella of Castile (1451-1504), and probably illuminated by Juan de Carrion, who was working in Avila in the 1470s and is mostly remembered for his illumination of the choir books of the cathedral of Avila. Other leaves or fragments of the manuscript were acquired by the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge University, and the Princes of Liechtenstein. In his Spanish Illumination J. Dominguez Bordona calls this manuscript “one of the most sumptuous and artistic series of choirbooks in all Spain.” See also the Grove Encyclopedia of Medieval Art and Architecture, vol. 2, p. 547.
  Provenance: Acquired in September 2015 by Laurent Ferri.
- Folio from a gradual., Ca. 1480.; Size: 282 x 225 mm. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Description: Single folio on vellum, from Eastern France or possibly Germany. Response, Versicle, and Offertory for the Octave of the Solemnity of the Sacred Heart of Jesus. Seven four-line staves in red (15.5 mm). Decorated with three staff-high initials in yellow wash, else rubricated. Trimmed in lower margin, some discoloration.
  Provenance: Acquired circa October 2015 by Laurent Ferri.
- Motu proprio by Pope Innocent VIII, 1488; Size: 330 x 190 mm. (Mapcase-folder 5bis)
  Description: Single folio on paper, Rome, dated 7 October "anno quarto" (1487), Latin in italic script. The document is mutilated on the right side with substantial loss of text. The lines "Fiat ut petitx si me videntem. I." and "Fiat ut [remainder torn away]" appear to be written in Pope Innocent VIII's own hand.
  Provenance: Acquired circa 1900 by Andrew Dickson White. First line is in a large, narrow script, with decorated initial.
- Papal bull signed by Innocent VIII, 1488; Size: 360 x 510 mm. (Mapcase-folder 5bis)
  Description: Single folio on vellum, dated 4 Id. Julii 1488, Latin in italic script, reserving the appointment of the Master of the Spanish order of St. James of Compostela
- Bifolium of relic list of St. Thiébaut in Thann, in German., Dated 1499.; Size: 309 x 101/205 mm (245 x 65 mm). (Box 4, Folder 21)
  Description: Complete bifolium on vellum in German. Single column, up to 34 lines, in red ink with occasional elaborate cadels. This unusual document records the re-organization of holy relics at the important medieval collegiate church of St. Thiébaut in Thann (founded 1332). Written in the East Oberdeutsch dialect of German and dated 1499, this complete text describes a transfer of saints’ relics in 1458, as overseen by the lay brothers Johannes Schürer, Michael Feyrlin, and Conrad Weyssman. The relics were removed from monstrances and organized in a reliquary, here called a Tafel, and therefore probably a box with cells carved from porphyry. When relocated, the relics were situated in individual cells given coordinates identified in our manuscript. Among a list of fourteen bones, two teeth, three pieces of fabric, and three splinters from the True Cross, is the tooth of the exceptionally rare Saint Aurelia. She accompanied Ursula and the 11,000 Virgins down the Rhine, but staying behind at Strasbourg due to illness, she missed the chance for martyrdom. The relics listed in this text include cloth from the Virgin’s robe and a tooth of Thann’s patron saint, Thiébaut. Faded mid seventeenth-century notes at the end of the text have not yet been deciphered.
  Provenance: Acquired by Laurent Ferri in 2013.
- Initial “B” with blue vine detail., Late fifteenth century to early sixteenth century.; Size: 102 x 111 mm (75 x 73 mm). (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Description: Illuminated initial “B” from a music manuscript with 4-line staves. Shape of “B” has been pricked into the manuscript prior to painting. The initial “B” is in gold, and surrounded by blue vines and enclosed by a red border.
  Provenance: Formerly folder 10.1
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_073_001.jpg (a).
- Initial “E” with grapes and flowers, from Italy., Late fifteenth century to early sixteenth century.; Size: 82 x 84 mm (73 x 73 mm). (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Description: Illuminated initial “E” from a music manuscript with 4-line staves. The gold initial “E” is decorated with grapes and blue and red flower details.
  Provenance: Formerly folder 10.2
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_072_001.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_072_002.jpg (b).
- Illumination from a choir book featuring illustration of St. Peter and assembled saints, from Italy., Early sixteenth century.; Size: 207 x 182 mm (207 x 182 mm). (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Description: In this illustration cut from a large choir book, St. Peter is shown in the center of the composition holding a key. Flanking him are St. Jerome and St. John the Baptist on the left, and St. Catherine and St. Lawrence on the right. Behind, a row of saints without attributes lead a host of other saints indicated by a further row of halos.
  Provenance: Obtained in Europe, circa 1895, by A. D. White. Formerly Calkins, no. 51; De Ricci, II, 1237, B. 49; folder 05.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_071_001.jpg (a).
- Leaf from an antiphonal for Good Friday, made in Saragossa, Spain, with intricate initials. Tiny pinpricks in both the regular and elegant "N" and "O" reveal that a compass was used., Early sixteenth century.; Size: 490 x 326 mm. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Description:.
  Provenance: Acquired by Laurent Ferri in December 2014.
- Illuminated vellum manuscript leaf from a book of hours., Late fifteenth century to early sixteenth century.; Size: 203 X 140mm. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Description: Page from a book of hours, the recto with a (later inserted) miniature painting (measuring approximately 90 X 61 mm) representing a kneeling nun, probably the patron who commissioned the book, introduced to the Virgin Mary by her patron saint. On the frame, one can read "S. A. BOURDEREUL"; on the verso, text with a full border of rinceaux, including gold ivy leaves on hairline stems as well as floral buds and acanthus leaves.
  Provenance: Acquired in 2015 by Virginia Cole and Laurent Ferri
- Bound document of a conveyance of a piece of olive grove near Cordoba (Spain), in Spanish., Dated 10th February 1503.; Size: 275 x 210 mm (204 x 155 mm). (Box 4, Folder 22)
  Description: Written in Spanish on parchment in a Cursiva script. Four leaves (two bound bifolia), approximately 35 lines per page; a few later annotations; stitched; some light soiling, sometime folded, modern summary in pencil on blank verso of final leaf, but generally in very good condition. A conveyance by Fernando Paez, son of Garcia Paez, and Ines del Cana Veral, wife of Fernando, citizens of Cordoba in the precinct of San Miguel, to Fernando, son of Fernando de Ecija, citizen of Cordoba, of a piece of olive grove near Cordoba in the district called Arroyo de los Peñas, for 16,000 marks. Notarially attested by Luis de Mesa, notary public of Cordoba. At the end (ff. 3v-4r) is a notarial certificate dated 14 Februrary 1503, of delivery of possession in the presence of Luis de Mesa and witnesses.
  Provenance: Acquired in Jan. 2014 by Laurent Ferri.
- Initial “S” with flowers and initial “Q” with landscape, from Italy., Sixteenth century.; Size: “S”: 62 x 62 mm. “Q”: 62/73 x 62 mm. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Description: Two gold decorated initials of “S” and “Q” probably from the same music manuscript with 4-line staves from Italy. The “S” initial is surrounded with red, pink, and yellow flower details. The “Q” initial contains a miniature landscape illustration in the bowl of the “Q”, with white-pink flowers in the bordering space. Both the “S” and “Q” initials have a border in gold.
  Provenance: Formerly folders 10.3 and 10.4.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_070_001.jpg (a, a); CornellMedMS_070_002.jpg (b, b).
- Leaf from a Gradual with musical notation and initials decorated with human faces., Sixteenth century.; Size: 519 x 370 mm (420 x 255 mm). Seven staves: 33 mm. (Mapcase-folder 7)
  Description: From Italy. Written in Latin on parchment in Gothic script. From a Gradual, with square musical notation on red, four-line staves. Two large initials, each decorated with the face of a man (one young and bearded, the other older and clean-shaven), and red rubrication. Text on hair side is somewhat faded.
  Provenance: Purchased in 2014.
- Single leaf from a Spanish Antiphonal (Santiago da Compostella, Spain), 1525; Size: 620 x 420 mm (530 x 340 mm). Six staves: 105 mm. (Mapcase-folder 6)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment. One leaf with text from the first antiphon for the Office of Vespers on the feast of All Saints. Decoration: an immense initial O measuring 170 x 175 mm in red and blue “puzzle” style infilled with impressively intricate pen work swirls within eight sections alternating in red and purple inks, all highlighted in contrasting colors. These same pen-work features, in the same colors, fill a dense border of "Moorish strap work" design on three sides.
  Provenance: Acquired in July 2014 by Laurent Ferri.
- Two bound leaves of a chirograph concerning the exchange of two watermills near Oxford., Dated 1596.; Size: Leaf 1: 105 x 315 mm (67 x 203 mm). Leaf 2: 107 x 334 mm (78 x 309 mm). (Box 4, Folder 23)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a late Cursiva Formata script. Two leaves are corded together and contain the same text. Typical of a chirograph, the top of the leaves have a wavy cut.
  Provenance: Formerly folder q.54.1-2.
- Fragment from the bottom border of a medieval book with a number of later hands., Probably late medieval parchment.; Size: 414/111 x 526 mm. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  Description: Remainder of a decorated initial evident at top of fragment, and evidence of pricking and ruling, but body of page cut away. Later eighteenth-/ nineteenth-century hands at bottom of page.
  Provenance: Donated by Fleda Meyers. Formerly folder 56.a